American Council of Learned Societies. Committee on Native American Languages. 1882-1958 Mss.497.3.B63c
American Philosophical Society
- Hupa
  - Hupa Indians, 1923; TMs with Ms, illus., 11 folders; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Maps.; Sketches.
- Inuktitut and Inupiaq ("Eskimo")
  - Eskimo ethnographic notes from Baffinland, 1885; AMs, 54L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In German. Probably Boas' original Baffinland field notes. Includes brief vocabulary, texts, and ethnography
    Freeman and Smith 1322
  - Eskimo folklore, 1901-1907; TMs and AMs, 68L., 18 drawings, 9 slips, 1 sheet; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Eskimo drawings, include pencil sketches of fishing, Repulse Bay; notes on Eskimo life; texts recorded directly in English. Obtained principally from Central Eskimo by George Comer, an American whaler-trader. Letter to Boas from J. S. Mutch, a Baffinland whaler, 1906.
    Freeman and Smith 1323
    Cf. Boas (1907)
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 2
  - Comparative word list of Alaskan Eskimo, Siberian Eskimo, and Chukchee, 1905; AMs, 32L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Ca. 1,200 items, arranged alphabetically by English with equivalents in parallel columns. Seward Peninsula and Point Barrow Eskimo
    Freeman and Smith 1345
  - Kungmit Eskimo vocabulary, 1935; AMs, 18L.; Francis, Alfred G.
    Obtained for Boas at Kotzebue, Alaska. Occasional red and black pencil additions in phonetic script. Names of animals, terms of relationship, parts of the body, natural objects,etc. 300items. Brief attempt at phonetic analysis.
    Freeman and Smith 1350
  - Eskimo texts, 1883-1929?; AMs, 18L, 13p., notebook; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Probably Boas and Wm. Thalbitzer. Texts and translations with occasional special vocabularies. Materials from Hamilton Inlet (Labrador), Hudson Bay, and Cumberland Sound. Eskimo syllabary is described; several texts in syllabary. Labrador material dated June, 1929,Thalbitzer.
    Freeman and Smith 1349
    Cf. Boas (1889, 1894, 1897)
  - Eskimo interlinear texts, 1889?; AMs Cy, 10L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Texts with interlinear translations, some apparently dating back to 1889.
    Freeman and Smith 1346
  - Eskimo lexicon, 1883?; AMs, ca. 2900 slips and cards; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In German-"Eskimo." Lexicon organized by Eskimo stem
    Freeman and Smith 1347
  - Eskimo songs, 1889?; AMs, 21L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Song texts with translation
    Freeman and Smith 1348
  - Drawings for "Property Marks of Alaskan Eskimo", 1899; AMs, 18 items; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Drawings from which the illustrations in Boas (1899) were reproduced
    Freeman and Smith 4249
    Donor, Frederica de Laguna, Oct. 1964
  - Greenlandic materials, 1936; AMs, 150L.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Rough notes used by the author in preparing his discussion of South Greenlandic (Eskimo). Based on S. Kleinschmidt (1851), and (1871)
    Freeman and Smith 1355
    Cf. Swadesh (1946)
  - Unaaliq Eskimo vocabulary file, 1951; Slip file, 800 items; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Vocabulary recorded in 1936 from James Andrews of St. Michael's Island, Alaska, with added comparative notes covering other Aleutian and Eskimo dialects. Organized phonetically by the Aleut. Based on 1936 vocabulary gained from James Andrews, No. 1350, as well as from published sources
    Freeman and Smith 1357
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, grantee, 1951. Printed, Swadesh (1952a):241-258
  - Unaaliq Eskimo field notes, 1936; TMs and AMs, 63L., 16L., 2 slips; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Vocabulary, paradigms, text
    Freeman and Smith 1356
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, 1951
  - Unaaliq and Proto Eskimo: comparative vocabulary, 1951; TMs Cy, 57 and 32L.; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    Two papers based on Unaaliq materials in No. 1356. Discussion of phonemes, morphophonemes, vocabulary. Synchronic and diachronic notes.
    Freeman and Smith 1358
    Donor, Morris Swadesh, grantee, n.d. Printed, Swadesh (1951); (1952a)
- Iowa
  - A descriptive grammar of the Ioway Indian language, 1936-1947; TMs with MS. additions, 19 l.; Whitman, William
    Based on field work with an Ioway and an Oto.
    Freeman and Smith 1631
- Iroquois
  - Iroquois notes, n.d.; AMs, 3p.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Taken at Hull, Province of Québec. Verb forms.
    Freeman and Smith 1848
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 10
  - Material on Iroquois dialects .., 1950; AMs and TMs, 191L. and 13 charts.; Hickerson, Harold, Geln D. Turner, and Nancy P. Hickerson
    Field report, field notes, word lists, data on sound-recording procedures. Biographical data on informants among Seneca, Cayuga, Onondaga, Oneida, Mohawk, Tuscarora, and Cherokee. Cf. No.1834. Letter from Harold Hickerson to C. F. Voegelin, n.d., and magnetic tape recording, mimeo 9p.
    Freeman and Smith 1835
    Cf. Hickerson, Turner, and Hickerson (1952).
    Donor, C. F. Voegelin, 1952.
- Isleta
  - Isleta word list, n.d.;ca.1921; AMs, 6L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Ca. 175 forms, principally plant names. Some lack English translations
    Freeman and Smith 1859
- Kalapuya
  - Kalapuya ethnology, ca.1918; TMs and AMS, 26L.; Frachtenberg, Leo Joachim, 1883-1930
    Organized ethnographic notes, referring to texts [No. 1866]: names, history, religion, ornaments, shamanism, social organizations, customs, and two songs. Essay on concept of soul. Franz Boas, "The expressions for some religious concepts of the Kwakiutl Indians, " May 20, 1926
    Freeman and Smith 1865
    Printed (Boas article only), Boas (1927) [in German] and Boas (1940) [in English]: 612-618
  - Sample of Atfalatin-Yamhalla dialect of Kalapuya, ca. 1928; TMs, 1 l.; Angulo, Jaime de
    Text on marriage customs with interlinear and incomplete free translations.
    Freeman and Smith 1868
    Cf. Angulo (1929) for discussion of field work.
  - Tfalati Kalapuya semasiology, ca.1930; TMs, 32L.; Angulo, Jaime de and Lucy S. Freeland
    Word lists semantically arranged; explanatory table. ca. 450 items
    Freeman and Smith 1869
  - Teton songs, n.d.; AMs, 2 notebooks.; Unidentified
    149 song scores, originally identified as Kalapuya, some with texts. No translations.
    Freeman and Smith 1867
  - Kalapuya word lists and texts, 1915-1930, esp. 1921; AMs, 111L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942, and Leo J. Frachtenberg
    A miscellany, not positively identified. Some Kwakiutl, Tsimshian, Salish, and some southwestern materials (Keresan?) are included. Reference numbers to printed texts in word lists, but the system is not that used by Boas.
    Freeman and Smith 1870
  - Kalapuya myths, ca. 1918; TMs Cy, 141 l.; Frachtenberg, Leo Joachim, 1883-1930
    Folkloristic texts with free translations and a few interlinear translations. Utilizes Atfalati folklore and ethnographic materials gathered by A. S. Gatschet, 1877, and field work in 1913 and 1914. Notes
    Freeman and Smith 1866
- Kalispel
  - Appendix to the Kalispel-English dictionary, compiled by the Missionaries of the Society of Jesus, 1879; TMs Cy, 36L.; Giorda, Joseph
    Typed copy of Giorda (1877-1879). Appendix. Also carbon copy. Both lack preface and pp. 35-36 of printed document.
    Freeman and Smith 1872
  - Kalispel grammar, ca. 1880; TMs, 137L.; Post, John
    A grammar, based in part on Giorda (18771879) and (1879), with an appendix which is, in part, a translation of Mengarini (1861). Apparently a copy prepared by Gladys A. Reichard in 1927 for the American Council of Learned Societies' Committee on American Native Languages.[Cf. No. 1910].
    Freeman and Smith 1874
  - Kalispel lexicon, n.d.; AMs, ca.610 cards.; Unidentified
    Root forms; examples taken from Giorda (1877-1879).
    Freeman and Smith 1873
- Karuk
  - Karok grammar, ca. 1930; TMs, 70L.; Harrington, John Peabody
    Incomplete. Sections on the numeral (methods of counting various things, arithmetical operations), interjections; the adjective, and free translation of a Karuk text.
    Freeman and Smith 1878
    Cf. Harrington (1930):121.
- Kathlamet
  - Kathlamet lexicon, 1890-1894; AMs, ca. 1500 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Lexical file arranged in part according to the English alphabet. Includes some Chinook; some Clackamas items. References to unknown texts.
    Freeman and Smith 1881
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 19
  - Kathlamet lexicon, 1890-1894; AMs, ca. 550 cards and 950 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Lexical file of forms with English equivalents. Part arranged alphabetically by English. Reference numbers apparently to field notes.
    Freeman and Smith 1880
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.7, reel 19-20
  - Kathlamet field notes, 1894-1895; AMs, 1 notebook.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Texts with interlinear translation. Reference numbers to printed version.
    Freeman and Smith 1879
    Printed in Boas (1901).
- Kato
  - Kato materials, 1902; 1906; AMs, 8 notebooks.; Goddard, Pliny Earle, 1869-1928
    Collected by Goddard at Laytonville, California; includes typed copy of word list [cf. No. 1603 for Pome duplicate] and texts. Lexical items with translations; ethnographic and material culture notes.
    Freeman and Smith 1882
    Cf. Goddard (1909), (1903a).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 43-44
- Kawaiisu
  - Kawaiisu phonetics and text, TMs Cy, 3L.; Zigmond, Maurice L.
    Text with partial interlinear translation "Coyote and Fox." Brief sketch of phonemes, word types, accent, etc.
    Freeman and Smith 1883
- Keresan
  - Keresan word list and linguistic notes, 1919-1928; TMs and AMS, 85L. 1 notebook.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Eight folders of Laguna and Cochiti grammatical, linguistic, folkloristic, and ethnographic materials
    Freeman and Smith 1886
    Cf. Boas (1928b) and (1923) for printed versions of several texts.
  - Keresan lexical file, n.d.;ca.1925; AMs, ca.8000 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Keresan forms with English equivalents. References to Boas MS. materials. Arrangement not clear, although some slips are tied together and separated by color or heavy cardboard.
    Freeman and Smith 1885
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 15-16
- Kickapoo
  - Kickapoo vocabulary, 1940; AMs, 2L; Swadesh, Morris, 1909-1967
    In Kickapoo-Spanish. Collected in Mexico.
    Freeman and Smith 1888
- Kiowa
  - Kiowa text and word list, AMs, 6L.; Unidentified
    Text and free translation; word list, Kiowa-English, 50 forms.
    Freeman and Smith 1889
- Koasati
  - Alibamu-Koasati and Creek vocabulary and texts, 1934; AMs, 1 notebook.; Swadesh, Morris, and Mary R. Haas, 1910-
    1 page biographical and locational data. 575 Koasati forms with English equivalents. 2 texts with interlinear translation. Miscellany. Also mixed Chitimacha-French-English forms from Mrs. Sadie Dardin, p. 73.
    Freeman and Smith 1890
- Kutenai
  - Folkloristic tales from the Salish area, 1900-1920; AMs, 19L.; Teit, James Alexander, 1864-1922
    Recorded directly in English from Shuswap, Okanagon, and Kutenai Indians
    Freeman and Smith 1893
  - Kutenai grammar, 1914-1920?; TMs and AMs, 242L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Grammatical sketch, list of forms, statements, kinship terms
    Freeman and Smith 1895
    Cf. Boas (1918): 313-352.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.6, reel 1
  - Kutenai texts with interlinear translations notebooks, 1914; AMs, 11 notebooks.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Freeman and Smith 1899
    Printed (some texts), Boas (1918). Cf. No. 1900 for copies.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 40
  - Kutenai texts, with interlinear translations and word lists, 1914; AMs, 1 notebook.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Linguistic notes and recopied versions of text from No. 1899 and No. 1901. Comparative table of contents prepared by John Yegerlehner (1959). Notes and kinship terms.
    Freeman and Smith 1900
    Printed (most texts), Boas (1918).
  - Kutenai lexicon, n.d.; 1918?; AMs, ca. 2500 cards and slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    References to published texts and list in Boas (1918). A few cards are Chukchee, according to Morris Swadesh.
    Freeman and Smith 1896
  - Kutenai lexicon, n.d.: ca. 1918?; AMs, 2, 000 cards and slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Lexicon refers to texts and lists in Boas (1918).
    Freeman and Smith 1897
  - Kutenai texts (with interlinear translation), word lists, and grammatical notes, 1914-1927; AMs, 1 notebook of 281L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Material used by Boas in his publications (1918) and (1926), with references in latter to former.
    Freeman and Smith 1901
  - Kutenai word list, n.d.;1918?; AMs, 39L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Kutenai-English vocabulary which is fuller than the list appearing in Boas (1918).
    Freeman and Smith 1902
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 40-41
  - Lexicon, n.d.; 1918?; AMs, ca.300 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    English-Kutenai lexical file. Orthography different from that employed by Boas in publications.
    Freeman and Smith 1903
  - Dictionary of the Kootenay language, 1891; AMs, 35L.; Chamberlain, Alexander F.
    Part H, Kootenay-English. Based on 1891 field work. "A" to "Agk."
    Freeman and Smith 1906
  - Kutenai materials, n.d.; 1891?; AMs and TMs, 262L., 4 slips. 6 notebooks.; Chamberlain, Alexander F.
    Kutenai lexicon, monograph on grammar, vocabulary, field notes on linguistics and physical anthropology. Upper and Lower Kutenai. Material on Chinook jargon and statements copied from Rev. Samuel Parker (1840). Images include photomechanical prints of weapons, dwellings, clothing.
    Freeman and Smith 1907
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 41
    Photomechanical prints
  - Abstracts from Kutenai grammar, nineteenth century; 1927?; TMs, 13L.; Post, John
    Prepared by Gladys Reichard for the American Council of Learned Societies. Includes a comparison of dialects from Dayton Creek, near Flathead Lake (Ksanka dialect), with those from Bonner's Ferry, Idaho (Akuklalgo dialect). Various Ksanka and Akuklalgo equivalents for English phrases appropriate to missionary work.
    Freeman and Smith 1910
  - Kutenai file-field notes, 1947; AMS, 791 slips; Garvin, Paul L.
    Slips for phrases from No. 1908, organized with references to informant and book in No. 1908 by initial, number of book, and page number.
    Freeman and Smith 1909
  - Kutenai field notes, taken from various informants, 1947; AMS, 66 notebooks.; Garvin, Paul L.
    Phrases taken from Lower Kutenai at Bonner's Ferry, Idaho; Cranbrook, B.C.; Creston, B.C.; and Elmo, Montana. Interlinear translation of phrases. Used in No. 1909.
    Freeman and Smith 1908
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 42
  - Grammar of the Kutenai language, 1894; TMs (translation), 317L.; Canestrelli, Phillippo
    Translation of Canestrelli (1894). Includes annotations by Franz Boas.
    Freeman and Smith 1904
    Printed, Canestrelli (1926) with annotations by Boas.
    Donor, C. F. Voegelin, 1947.
  - Traditions and information regarding the Tonaxa, 1913; AMs and TMs, 15p. 8L.; Teit, James Alexander, 1864-1922
    Remarks on the Tonaxa language, words and phrases; data from several sources as to origins, habitat, and disappearance of the Tonaxa. TMs adapted from these notes.
    Freeman and Smith 1894
    Printed version, Teit (1930b).
  - Kutenai miscellaneous grammatical notes, n.d.; AMs and TMs, 102p.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    An incomplete grammar, devoted principally to verb forms, nouns, and pronouns. A section on numerals is printed in Boas (1926).
    Freeman and Smith 1898
    Cf. Canestrelli (1926) and Boas (1926).
- Kwakiutl
  - Kwakiutl folklore and ethnography, 1935; TMs Cy, 176p.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Kwakiutl ethnography compiled by Boas from George Hunt MS. materials, with page references to Hunt materials and publications.
    Freeman and Smith 1918
    Cf. No. 1917
  - Kwakiutl autobiography, 1930; TMs and AMs, 128L.; Averkieva, Julie
    Field notes obtained at Alert Bay and Fort Rupert. Personal documents concern ethnography: culture and folklore.
    Freeman and Smith 1912
  - Abstracts of Kwakiutl tales, n.d.; TMs Cy, 172 l., 201 l.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Abstracts of tales found in various Boas publications, with references to original in margin. Carbon and original have some pages not found in the other.
    Freeman and Smith 1913
  - Kwakiutl ethnographic materials, 1918-1926; TMs and AMs, 234L. 3 photos.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Relates to gathering, preservation, and preparation of foods. TMs from Hunt MS. material, with marginal references to Hunt MS.; some Hunt MS. pages; music scores. Includes two letters of George Hunt to Boas, 1925-1926.
    Freeman and Smith 1915
  - Kwakiutl ethnographic notes, 1918-1931; TMs and AMs, 341L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Continuation of material in No. 1915 suprcl. Typed transcripts from Hunt MS. Miscellaneous notes on linguistics, material culture, etc. Texts. Images include photographs of skull form, cyanotypes, pencil sketches of Bella Coola houses. Includes letter of George Hunt to Boas, 1931.
    Freeman and Smith 1916
    Cyanotypes; Gelatin silver prints; Sketches.
  - Kwakiutl ethnographic materials, 1900-1931; TMs and AMs, 446L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942 and George Hunt
    Boas' notes, some used in preparation of Boas (1909a). Hunt MS. histories of Naxalkem and half Balbala tribes; also Guzayaedox. Texts, some with interlinear translation, which relate to manufacturing are in unbound journal book. Numerous pages of Hunt MS.; vocabulary lists, brief texts. 9 letters of George Hunt to Boas, 1900-1931, on Kwakiutl ethnography and orthography. Images include pencil sketches of maps, nets.
    Freeman and Smith 1927
  - History of twenty coppers from Alert Bay, n.d. (1924?); TMs, 137p., 21pl.; Hunt, George
    Comment of Edward Sapir, attached, states this is a transcript of "Growing-up-like-one-who-has-a-grandmother." Critical comment by J. D. Leechman. Images include photographs of totem figures.
    Freeman and Smith 1932
  - Remarks on masks and ceremonial objects of the Kwakiutl, before 1924; TMs with MS. emendations, 28L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    An unpublished article of Boas which amplifies and corrects explanations of specimens illustrated in Boas (1897). References to figures and plates in that work. Boas provides information on ownership and more accurate information on use based on subsequent field trips.
    Freeman and Smith 1926
    Cf. Boas (1897).
  - Miscellaneous anthropological notes, n.d.; AMs, 22L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942, et al.
    Incomplete essay on Kwakiutl dances (Boas). Notes [Wakashan comparison], E. Sapir. Museum items listed by J. A. Teit. Description and sketch of cranium found in 1886 near Victoria, B.C. (prepared for World's Columbian Exposition) Includes photographs of Catawba, fragments of 16 mm film.
    Freeman and Smith 1928
    Gelatin silver prints; Sketches.
  - Kwakiutl personal names, n.d.; AMs, ca. 375 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    75 Indian names with English translation; 100 untranslated.
    Freeman and Smith 1942
  - Personal names, n.d.; AMs, 20 cards.; Unidentified
    Apparently Kwakiutl; mostly untranslated.
    Freeman and Smith 1953
  - Kwakiutl materials, 1896-1933; AMs and TMs, 1720L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Materials submitted to Boas by George Hunt, with several covering letters. Includes both analytic and serial tables of contents, conversational texts, word lists with detailed discussions of meanings. Some texts are in English only. Printed Hunt materials are omitted.
    Freeman and Smith 1941
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 21-22
  - Kwakiutl music and songtexts, AMs, 1 notebook. 12p; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Contains music with and without text.
    Freeman and Smith 1919
  - Kwakiutl personal names, n.d.; AMs, 184 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    File of names classified by stems and some by suffixes.
    Freeman and Smith 1943
  - Kwakiutl social organization, n.d.; AMs, 193 cards.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Each card lists names, tribe, phratry, position, kinship, social potlatch relation.
    Freeman and Smith 1920
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 22
  - Kwakiutl songs, 1922-1930; AMs and TMs, 572L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    MS. song texts with 80p. typescript and carbon. Musical scores, transcribed by Kolinski. References to recordings.
    Freeman and Smith 1921
  - Kwakiutl texts, 1893-1897; AMs, 1 notebook, ca. 110p.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Contains texts, including some song texts with interlinear translation and notes on vocabularies; list of phonograph cylinders and list of items which have been published. See Boas (1935):238-240; 221-225. Derived from Hunt MS., but rewritten by dictation to Boas (in notebook).
    Freeman and Smith 1945
    rinted, Boas (1897):665-686.
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.1, reel 50
  - Kwakiutl texts, 1894-1895; AMs, 7 notebooks.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Contains texts with some interlinear translations. A few brief Haida texts. A few songs with 1 sheet of musical scores and texts. Some shorthand notes
    Freeman and Smith 1946
  - Maps of Vancouver Island, with Kwakiutl place names, 1934?; Maps, 5 items; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    MS. map (or tracing) of Map 21, Garden Beds of the Nimkish in Boas (1934). 4 printed maps of Vancouver Island with MS. additions showing place names of Kwakiutl and Comox.
    Freeman and Smith 1924
  - Personal names in Kwakiutl, 1925- ?; AMs and TMS, part Cy, 328L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    List, alphabetized by Kwakiutl, of names of persons, names of tribes, names of places. Source: Boas (1895), (1925a), (1921), and Boas and Hunt (1905), and various manuscripts.
    Freeman and Smith 1949
  - Kwakiutl and Koskimo notes, AMs, 75L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    English text written by a native Koskimo with continuation by Boas. Boas' shorthand notes on backs of pages.
    Freeman and Smith 1914
  - Kwakiutl personal names and place names, AMs, ca. 1,200 slips.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Collected by Boas and others.
    Freeman and Smith 1944
    Printed (in part), Boas (1934).
  - Kwakiutl ethnographic materials, 1926-1928; AMs and TMs, 143L.; Hunt, George
    Materials relating to seating; genealogies; houses; food and cooking; burial and magic. Song texts included. Three letters, Hunt to Boas, December 7, 1926; June 4 and June 15, 1928, enclosing manuscript material.
    Freeman and Smith 1933
  - Kwakiutl texts, 1894; AMs, 6L.; Hunt, George
    Text with interlinear translation: "How the Salmon came into the world."
    Freeman and Smith 1952
    Microfilmed as: Film 372, reel 23
  - Note on Kwakiutl negative forms, n.d.; ALS, 1L.; Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939
    Undated letter to Franz Boas.
    Freeman and Smith 1955
  - Kwakiutl grammar, 1948; TMs, 950L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    Phonology, morphology, syntax with appendices on Newettee dialect, Bella Bella. Dictionary of suffixes.
    Freeman and Smith 1939
    Donor, Mrs. Helene Boas Yampolsky, 1948. Printed, Boas (1947).
    Microfilmed as: Film 372.6, reel 5
  - Kwakiutl ethnographic texts with translation, 1948; TMs, 742L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    In two parts: contents and 289 texts; free translation of texts.
    Freeman and Smith 1938
    Donor, Mrs. Helene Boas Yampolsky, 1946.
  - List Of Kwakiutl manuscripts by George Hunt in Columbia University library, 1942; TMs Cy, 15L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    A list giving contents, whether published or translated, for pages of Hunt, 1-5850 (some omissions). Unpublished pages listed as "phototyped." Carbon copy of an earlier list with notation that unprinted items are to be photographed.
    Freeman and Smith 1923
    Donor, Mrs. Helene Boas Yampolsky, 1946
  - Kwakiutl dictionary, ed. by Helene Boas Yampolsky, 1948; TMs, part Cy, 453L.; Boas, Franz, 1858-1942
    An alphabetical listing of forms according to the Kwakiutl; detailed discussions of meanings. A companion to the grammar, No. 1939.
    Freeman and Smith 1937
    Donor, Zellig S. Harris, 1948